Guide to the Henry H. Douglas papers, 1945-1992
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Henry H. Douglas papers
1960-1974
1945-1992
C0296
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
0.75 linear ft.
Notes, articles, correspondence and other materials regarding information on Prince William County and surrounding areas.
Douglas, Henry H., 1903-1987
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the Prince William County Library in November 2016.
Biographical Information
Henry H. Douglas (1903-1987) founded and became the executive director of the Pioneer America Society in 1967. Douglas had been a resident of Falls Church, Virginia. Douglas was an editor of Pioneer America and of Echoes of History, publications of the Pioneer America Society, in the 1960s and 1970s. They published many articles about historic sites in northern Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Henry H. Douglas papers contain many notes, correspondence, articles, interview transcripts, images and other materials about historic places in Prince William County and surrounding areas. One area of focus in these papers is Beverley Mill, a historic grist mill near Broad Run, VA. His notes and collected materials are mostly from the 1960s and 1970s.
Arrangement
The Henry H. Douglas papers are arranged by subject.
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center also holds the .The Library of Virginia and the Fairfax County Library have portions of the Henry H. Douglas papers.
Index Terms
Geographical Names:
Prince William County (Va.); Virginia, Northern--History.
Contents List
- Henry H. Douglas papers, 1945-1992
  - VA-Prince William-Barns, Articles, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Henry H. Douglas Biography, 1989, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - VA-Prince William-Ben Lomond Article, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - VA-Prince William/Bel Air Articles and Misc., 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - VA-Prince William-Bridges, Articles, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - VA-Prince William/Buckland, Articles and Notes, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - VA-Prince William/Buckland Hall, Excerpts from 18th and 19th Centuries, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - VA-Prince William/Buckland Tavern Re: E. H. Pierce, Articles, Corres. And Notes, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - VA-Prince William/Buckland Tavern, Notes and Articles, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - VA-Prince William/Buckland, Notes, Interview Trans. and Articles, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - VA-Prince William/Bull Run Mountain Article, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - VA-Prince William/Catharpin, Articles, Notes, Card, 1973, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - VA-Prince William/Cloverland, Notes and Correspondence, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - VA-Prince William-Churches, Articles and Notes, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - VA-Prince William-Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - VA-Prince William/Dumfries, Articles and Misc., 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - VA-Prince William/Dumfries-Henderson, Images and Essays, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - VA-Prince William/Falkland, Interviews and Notes, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - VA-Prince William-Farms, Articles, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - VA-Prince William/Gainesville, Notes, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - VA-Prince William/Greenwich, Notes, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - VA-Prince William-Growth, Articles, 1968, 1973, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - VA-Prince William/Haymarket-Woodlawn, Corresp. and Sketches, 1971; 1890 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - VA-Prince William/Haymarket, Articles and Correspondence, 1968-1974; 1930s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - VA-Prince William-Historic Sites Survey, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - VA-Prince William-Houses, Articles, 1960s-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - VA-Prince William/Manassas Battlefield, Articles, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - VA-Prince William/Manassas, Articles, 1969-1975; 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - VA-Prince William/Nokesville, Articles, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - VA-Prince William-Parks, Articles, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - VA-Prince William/Occoquan, Articles and Misc., 1967-1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - VA-Prince William-People, Articles, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - VA-Prince William/Portici, Miscellaneous Materials, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - VA-Prince William/Quantico, Articles, circa 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - VA-Prince William-Railroads, Articles, 1971, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - VA-Prince William Articles, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - VA-Prince William-Schools, Article, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - VA-Prince William-Stores, Articles, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - VA-Prince William/Sudley, Articles, Corresp., Misc., 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - VA-Prince William/Thorofare, Article and Notes, circa late 1960s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - VA-Prince William/Woodbridge, Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - VA-Prince William/Brentsville, Articles, 1971, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - VA-Prince William/Rippon Lodge, Articles, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - VA-Prince William-History, Notes and Articles, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - VA-Prince William/Manassas, Newspaper, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Beverley Mill Article and Notes; BM-2, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Beverley Mill Research Notes; BM-6, circa 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Beverley Mill, Notes of No Further Use; BM-9, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - VA-Prince William/Beverley Mill Images, Articles, and Notes; BM-1, 1937; circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chapman Family, Notes and Book Photocopy; BM-3, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Beverley Mill, Notes; BM-4, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Beverley Mill, Interviews; BM-5, 1971, 1977, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Beverley Mill- NOVA Heritage, Notes, Corresp., and Articles; BM-7, 1973, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - VA-Prince William/Beverley Mill Background Material, Interviews, Etc.; BM-8, 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - VA-Prince William/Beverley Mill Articles, Notes, Etc.; BM-10, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - VA-Prince William/Occoquan River, Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Deed Book Page 370, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Wills and Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sales Slips-Beverley Mills/Broad Run, VA, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sales Slips-Beverley Mills/Broad Run, VA, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sales Slips-Beverley Mills/Broad Run, VA, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Old Fashioned Corn Meal Advertisement and Bag, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)